Hello students! In today's chapter, we are going to learn all about animals. Do you have any pet animals? How do you look after your pet animal? Today we will explore Animal Life.
Animals are living beings like us which are found in nature. Animals are found all over the world and they need food, shelter, air, and water like other living beings, to grow and survive. Their size, eating habits, body colour, and body covering vary according to the place they are found in. All animals need care and protection.
Animals live both on land and in water. Animals that live in water are called Water Animals or Aquatic Animals. Animals that live on land are called Land Animals. Lion, elephant, and tiger are land animals.
Birds are the animals with feathers, wings, two legs, and a beak without teeth. The duck, pigeon, and parrot are examples of birds.
Very small animals are called Insects. They have six legs. Some insects have wings to fly. Butterfly, housefly, and grasshopper are examples of insects.
Animals that are kept at home or around our homes are called domestic animals. They are useful to us. Some animals like the dog, parrot, and rabbit are kept as pets. We love them and take care of them.
Some animals can be seen only in the forests. They are called wild animals. The tiger and lion are wild animals.
Animals need homes to live and food to grow. Different animals eat different kinds of food and live in different homes.
Lions live in caves in forests. These caves are called dens. Lions eat the flesh of other animals. Rabbits are burrowing animals and live in burrows. Rabbits eat vegetables.
Birds build their own nests. They eat seeds, berries, fruit, insects, and so on. Ants make a hill-like structure using sand called an anthill. Ants live in a group like bees.
Domestic and pet animals are kept in human-made homes. A dog lives in a kennel. A cow lives in a shed. A horse lives in a stable.
Let us recall. Animals live on land or in water. Birds have feathers, wings, two legs, and a beak. Insects are small animals with six legs. Domestic animals may live near people. Wild animals live in natural places. Different animals have different homes and foods.
Glossary. Birds are animals that can fly. Insects are very small animals. Domestic animals are animals that can be kept at home. Wild animals are animals that live in the jungle. A den is the place where lions live.
Answer the questions. Name any two pet animals. Where are dogs kept? What do the birds build? Fill in the blanks: Rabbits live in a blank. Birds have a blank to fly. Animals that live in water are called a blank. Insects have blank legs. Ants live in a group like blank.
Choose the correct answer. Fish live in: water, land, or both water and land. Animals that live on land are called: land, water, or none of these animals. A butterfly is a: bird, insect, or none of these. Parrot and rabbit are: wild, pet, or insect animals. A tiger is: a domestic, wild, or pet animal.
Activity: Draw any animal of your choice and name it. Life Skills: Animals also have feelings. Do not hurt animals. They will be friendly to us. Protect animals.